Hi, and welcome to step two of the tribe success path. Step two is called activate the application.
And the reason we call it that is we're taking all the knowledge you learned in step one,
and we're learning to apply it to exam style questions. Now it's really important that we
do that topic by topic because each topic has a different set of exam techniques and a different
set of exam tips that will really help you augment your grade. So it's important that you activate
the application for each topic. The way we're going to do that is you're going to download
the past paper questions below and I've handpicked them to relate exactly to what we've just learned.
You're going to complete those questions. You're going to put your head down,
you're going to work really hard and complete those questions.
Once you've completed those questions, you're going to watch me screencast the answers
to most of them in the rest of this tutorial. Now the reason I've screencast the answer to about
two thirds of these questions and not the last third is we need to start letting you go.
And what that means is I have to teach you all my exam tips, I have to teach you all my exam
techniques. You have to start taking them in and applying them and that's step three of the
tribe success path. That's propel your progress. So you have to do some work in this step,
you have to learn my exam techniques, learn my tips and do your own work for step three
to work effectively. So once you've written out the answers to these past paper questions,
keep them and take them on to step three. Okay let's go.
Question one, a stone is falling at a constant velocity vertically down a tube filled with oil.
Which of the following statements about the energy changes of the stone during its motion
are correct? Let's think about this stone, it's falling with a constant velocity downwards and
that's due to the weight of the stone. There's a force, an equal and opposite force of drag
acting back up the way. Because it is falling down, it will be losing
potential energy. If it's going at a constant velocity, it will have kinetic energy and it
will also be gaining some thermal energy. Because of the friction, it will be gaining
thermal energy. So which of the statements are true? The gain in kinetic energy is less
than the loss in gravitational potential energy. Well kinetic energy is constant,
the gain in kinetic energy is zero. So kinetic energy gain is zero but it is losing gravitational
potential energy. So this is true. Number two, the sum of kinetic and gravitational potential
energy of the stone is constant. This would only be true if there was no frictional forces.
If we go back to the law of conservation of energy, the total energy of a system is conserved
assuming no external forces apply. Well friction is applying here and some of that energy will
be lost to heat. So that's not true. Number three, the work done by the force of gravity
has the same magnitude as the work done by friction. The work done by the force of
gravity is force times distance and the work done by the force of friction is force times distance.
The forces are the same because it's travelling at a constant speed. So the forces are the same.
The distance travelled due to the work done by these forces is the same because it's travelling
at a constant velocity. So yes, this is true. The answer is B. Question two, a company designs
a spring system for loading ice blocks onto a truck. The ice block is placed in a holder H
in front of the spring and an electric motor compresses a spring by pushing H to the left.
So this will be elastic energy in here. When the spring is released, the ice block is accelerated
towards the ramp ABC. When the spring is fully decompressed, the ice block loses contact with
spring at A. The mass of the ice block is 55 kilograms. Assume the surface of the ramp
is frictionless. So that means it's a constant speed and it will have kinetic energy and that
the masses of the spring and the holder are negligible compared to the mass of the block.
So what will happen is the block will travel at constant speed across here and then it will
travel up this ramp. The block arrives at C with a speed of 0.9 meters per second. Show that the
elastic energy stored in the spring is 670 joules. Well, elastic energy has the equation half
kx squared. But we don't know any of those things. We don't know the extension of the spring. We
don't know the spring constant. So we have to think of another way of doing it. Aha!
Wait a minute. We know that all the elastic energy turns into kinetic energy and gravitational
potential energy. And up here it will have kinetic energy because it'll still be moving and we can
see that it's still moving here. And potential energy. So if we can work out what the sum of
kinetic energy and potential energy is at C then we can work out what the elastic energy is.
We can do that. So a half times the mass of the block which is 55 times the speed which is 0.9
squared plus 55 times 9.81 times the height which is 1.2 gives us a value of 669.7 joules
which is of course given to two significant figures because the rest of the data is given
to two significant figures. That's A1. A2. Calculate the speed of the block at A. At A,
this point here, there is no potential energy. So all of the elastic energy is transferred to kinetic
energy at that point. So we have 670 equals a half mv squared. V is equal to the square root
of 2 times 670 divided by the mass which is 55 and if we work that through that's 4.9 meters per second.
Question 3. A student of weight 600 newtons climbs a vertical ladder 6 meters tall in a time of 8
seconds. What is the power developed by the student against gravity? So the student is doing work
against gravity and the power is equal to work done over time but we know that work done is equal
to energy transferred so therefore power is energy transferred over time. But what is the transfer
of energy here? Well he's gaining potential energy so actually the equation for power here is mgh which
is potential energy over time which is oh mg is the weight so that's 600 newtons times the height
which is 6 divided by 8 so that's 3600 divided by 8 which will give us 450 watts. The answer
is D. Question 4. The diagram below shows part of a downhill ski course which starts at point A
50 meters above the level ground. Point B is 20 meters above the level ground so that means
that A to B is basic maths 30 meters. A skier of mass 65 kilograms starts from rest at point A
and during the ski course some of the gravitational potential energy is transferred to kinetic energy.
From A to B 24% of the gravitational potential energy transferred to kinetic energy show that
velocity at B is 12 meters per second. Okay so the loss of potential energy from A to B
is equal to E P equals m g the change in height which is 65 times 9.81 times the loss of height
which is 30. That means that it is losing 19,129.5 joules of potential energy. Now 24% of that
is transferred to kinetic energy so the kinetic energy at B is equal to 24% of 19,129.5
which gives us a value of 4591.08 joules. That's how much kinetic energy it's got at B.
We want to use that value to find out what the speed of the object at B is. I know I'm using
too many decimal places and significant figures I just want to stay accurate until we get the final
answer. So V equals the square root of 2 times 4591.08 divided by 65 which gives us a value of 11.9
meters per second. Of course everything is to two significant figures so the answer is 12 meters
per second at which is what it said in the question. Fabulous! Question five a motor of
input power 160 watts raises a mass of 8 kilograms vertically at a constant speed of 0.5 meters per
second. What is the efficiency of the system? Oh I'm going to give you an exam tip! When you're
thinking of power I know you often think of the idea of work done over time or energy transferred
over time. Oh why am I writing this out it's taking ages. Actually sometimes when you're looking
at a mechanical system or something that's moving a very quick formula for power which is useful is
force times velocity. Put that in the memory bank okay. So when we're looking at efficiency
we're looking at the useful output power over the total input power. Useful output power right
well that's the power that your man's using right so it's force so it is 8 times 10 that's the force
because that says weight times the velocity is 0.5 and the total input power is 160.
Oh you'll notice I've used 10 there by the way for gravity. If we're doing multiple choice questions
it's not worth getting into small details like 9.8 that's my that's my view anyway
because we're looking at 80 times it's 40 divided by 160 so our efficiency is 25 percent. Exam tip
is power equals force times velocity is a very useful formula to remember. Question six an object
falls from rest from a height of h close to the surface of the moon. The moon has no atmosphere
just like a physics Christmas party. When the object has fallen to a height of h over 4
above the surface what is the ratio of kinetic energy of the object h over 4 over gravitational
potential energy of the object h? My goodness what a mouthful. Okay well we can do this one
easily the bottom denominator is just mgh or let's just call it ep. So the key for us is to
work out what the kinetic energy of the object is at h over 4. Well we know that ep at the start
will equal to ep at h over 4 plus ek at h over 4 and ep at h over 4 is equal to ep over 4
plus ek so ek is equal to ep minus ep over 4 so ek is equal to three quarters ep.
Now if we pop that up here and the ratio then is three quarters ep over ep these two cancel the
ratio as three quarters e. The tension in a horizontal spring is directly proportional to
the extension of the spring. What that's basically saying is this relationship holds true. The energy
stored in the spring at extension x is e. What is the work done by the spring when its extension
changes from x to x over 4? Now here's my exam trip whenever you see the word work done
and we're looking at energy I always write down work done equals energy transferred. It is a super
useful thing to have in your brain to remind you how to do these things. We know what the elastic
energy is at x but what is the elastic energy at x over 4? Well it's half k x over 4 all squared
which is a half k x squared over 16 which is basically e over 16. So the energy transferred
between x and x4 is e minus e over 16 so it's 15e over 16. That's the energy transfer going from x
to x over 4 which is equal to the work done so the answer is d. Question eight. A ball is
thrown vertically upwards, air resistance is negligible. What is the variation with time
of the kinetic energy of the ball? Let's think about this ball. It's going to be
very fast to begin with so kinetic energy is going to be maximum at t equals naught.
That rules out this one. It's eventually going to get to the point at the top of the
trajectory where e k equals zero. So in the middle we're looking for e k to be zero.
That's correct. That's correct and that's correct. Kinetic energy is a scalar.
That means we're not really interested in direction and it can't be a negative
so that rules out a. So we're looking at b or d. There's no linear function to this. I can't see
this b being correct because there's nothing linear about kinetic energy. It's got v squared
in it. It's a parabola. I don't see it so I'm saying it's not b. I'm saying it's d.
Question nine. Before I start question nine I know what you were thinking when you tried this.
You were thinking it's impulse and there's lots of momentum. Why is Sally making me do this? Well
you will know that IB physics all links together. The ultimate exam will be a linking of concepts.
That's the whole point of the new syllabus. You have to start doing problems of topics that you
have done before and eventually this will work into the work done on the ball. So let's go
with this. Let's put all our effort into it and see how much you remember from a2. Question nine.
The graph shows the variation with time of the horizontal force exerted on a tennis ball
by a racket and we can see this graph here. A force time graph. You'll be alerted from a2 to
remember that the area under a force time graph is equal to impulse. A tennis ball was stationary
at the instant when it was hit. The mass of the tennis ball is this. So let's write some stuff
down. The area under the curve so we know the impulse is area under the curve is 0.84 Newton
second. If we didn't remember the area under the curve is equal to impulse then the units of this
would give you a clue. Calculate the speed of the ball as it leaves the racket. So a.
a. j which is the impulse equals the change in momentum which is m v minus m u which is m v minus
u. Now u is 0 so j is equal to m v. v equals j over m so 0.84 divided by 5.8 times 10
to the minus 2 gives us a value of 14.5 meters per second. That's a. b. Show that the average force
exerted on the ball by the racket is about 50 newtons. Again the word average force tells me
it's impulse. That's a little exam trick from a2. Average force times time equals impulse.
The average force here we want to find out so it's impulse divided by time. Impulse is 0.84.
What's the time? The time over which this ball was in contact with the racket. You can see it
starts at 12 milliseconds and ends at 28 milliseconds. That means it's in contact with the racket for
16 milliseconds. So 0.84 divided by 16 milliseconds is 52.5 newtons which is around about 50 newtons
which is what the question asked. Perfect. b. Determine with reference to the work done by
the average force, the horizontal distance travelled by the ball while it was in contact
with the racket. Okay I'm gonna write c up here. I've seen the word work done so I'm just gonna
write down this just to see if it helps. Work done equals energy transferred. We know work done
is equal to average force in this case times distance. We know what the average force is,
we don't know what the distance is but what we can do is work out the energy transferred because
this ball has ultimately gained kinetic energy hasn't it? It's transferred into kinetic energy.
So d is equal to half mv squared over the average force.
We know a half times the mass of the ball, I'm writing very small I'm so sorry, times 14.5
squared divided by the average force which is 52.5 gives us a distance of 0.119 meters. We'll
do that again. Okay again you've found this idea of work done equals energy transferred as a real
helping point or a starting point when you're dealing with work done questions. Question 10.
A net force F acts on an object of mass m that is initially at rest. The object moves in a
straight line. The variation of F with distance is shown. Okay exam tip alert whenever you see
a force distance graph you write the words area equals work done underneath it like that.
What is the speed of the object at distance s1? So what's the speed here?
At this point it's got kinetic energy and we know that work done is equal to energy
transferred. It's gained kinetic energy from zero that means the area is equal to the kinetic
energy and we can work out the area just using algebra because it's a triangle
and the area of a triangle is a half base times height. So the area of this triangle is half
s1 F1 and it's equal to kinetic energy which is a half m v squared. So we can get rid of those
halves because there's a half on each side and we can rearrange for v. V squared is equal to
s1 F1 over m so v is equal to the square root of s1 F1 over m and that relates to b. Question 11.
A cyclist rides up a hill of vertical height of 100 meters in 500 seconds at constant speed.
The combined mass of the cyclist and the bicycle is 80 kilograms. The power developed by the
cyclist is 200 watts so that's the power in. What's the efficiency of the energy transfer
in the system? So the efficiency is the power out or the useful power out divided by the total
power in and I think we'll use that little equation that I told you about earlier power
is equal to Fv over 200 and the force is the weight of this guy so it's 800 times the speed
which is 100 over 500 divided by 200 160 divided by 200 that gives us a value of 80 percent.
Question 12. It's another one of these questions that involves material from previous topics
but we can't get away from that all right. A ball of mass 0.25 kilograms is released from rest
at time t equals naught from a height h above a horizontal floor. The graph shows the variation
with time t of the velocity v of the ball. Air resistance is negligible. Take g to equal
9.8 meters per second squared. The ball reaches the floor after one second. Determine h. So we
want to find out what the height of this ball is when it drops. I can see two immediate methods
here. My first method is to recognize that the area under a velocity time graph is equal to
displacement. So if I can find the area of this triangle I can find the height of the ball.
Why am I specifically using this triangle? Well I know that the ball reaches the floor after one
second so the area under the graph until one second is the area that I'm interested in and
the area of this graph is a half base times height so it's a half times one times ten.
So the answer is five meters. That's it five meters. If that seems too easy for you let's use
the Suvat equations Suvat. We want to find out what s is. We know that u is zero. V the final
speed is ten. We can see that there. A is 9.8 and you'll notice I haven't done minus ten
or minus 9.8 because I've chosen positive to be downwards but if you put minus in there
it'll work too. And t is equal to one. So we can use any Suvat equation. Let's go with the easiest.
s equals ut plus a half at squared. u is zero. s equals a half times 9.8 times one squared
which gives us 4.9 meters. You'll notice that this answer here, 4.9 meters,
is different to five meters but the examiner will give you either of those
correct as long as you've shown you're working. B1. Label the time and velocity graph using the
letter m, the point where the ball reaches a maximum rebound height. So maximum rebound
height means it's bounced on the floor and it's got back up to its point where it's maximum
height. First thing I would say about that, at this stage v will be equal to zero. So we notice
either this point here or this point here. Or, sorry, this point at the start. All right, so
we know that this point here is where it's just hit the ground and within that point one of a
second it changes direction and starts to travel upwards again in the opposite direction with
velocity. So this point here where it hits zero must be the maximum rebound height. Draw on the axis
a graph to show the variation with time of the height of the ball from the instant it rebounds
from the floor until the instant it reaches maximum rebound height. If it rebounds from the
floor it's going to start at zero. Maximum height is going to be here. Let's just say
max height there and we want to know what shape to make it. We know that it will gain
height very quickly and then as the velocity of the of the ball starts to slow, the height of the
ball will start to slow at the same rate. So what we'll find is the graph looks like this and
I've just missed my max point, just make it a bit bigger, like that. On to c. Estimate the loss
in mechanical energy of the ball as a result of the collision with this floor. What does that mean?
Okay so it's collides with the floor here and it's got a certain amount of energy there
and then after collision with the floor it's got energy here so E1 and E2.
It's got kinetic energy at both points but the kinetic energy is different. So if we can find
out the kinetic energy at point one and then the kinetic energy at point two and find the
difference in those two we'll find the loss in mechanical energy. I'm now trying to remember all
of the values. What was the mass of this object? It was 0.25 times and it had
10 meters per second before it hit the ground. After it hit the ground it's got five
so half times 0.25 times five squared which gives us a value of 9.4 joules. That's the loss
in mechanical energy of the ball as a result of the collision with the floor. Determine the average
force exerted on the floor by the ball. Average force I'm thinking of impulse.
F T equals m v minus m u so F is equal to m v minus m u over T so 0.25.
V is final speed so that's five minus the initial speed which is minus 10
over T and the time in contact with the wall was 0.1 seconds. Let me show you to prove.
0.1 seconds. So the answer there is if I pop it all into the calculator 37.5 Newtons
and D2 suggest why the momentum of the ball if I missed a question. Oh yeah I have look
B2 state the acceleration of the ball at maximum rebound height. State means the answer is in
the question. It's either in the graph or it's in the question. Okay state the acceleration of
the ball at maximum rebound height. Well anything in free fall, anything that's a projectile,
anything that's flying about in the earth's surface has the same acceleration at all times.
The acceleration of the ball is the force due to gravity and in this question it says 9.80
meters per second. Sorry I missed that. Now we can do D2. Suggest why the momentum of the
ball was not conserved during the collision with the floor. So what the ball does
is that it collides with the floor and so it goes down like this and then collides back up again
and it changes in momentum but what the floor does is part of the system is it recoils slightly
maybe shakes a little bit and that shaking of the floor has momentum as well.
So this question says suggest why the momentum of the ball was not conserved. Well one
the momentum of the system of the of the ball and floor
oops system was conserved some of the ball's energy, oh not energy, some of the ball's
momentum was transferred to the floor. Now I made a big mistake there. I said some of the
ball's energy was transferred and actually I made that mistake because a lot of students make that
mistake. When you're talking about the law of conservation of energy and the law of conservation
of momentum they are two very clear and distinct concepts. Make sure you don't make the mistake
that I just made. Okay question 13 what is equivalent to the ratio of specific energy of a fuel
over energy density of a fuel and remember in Mass of the Majority step one of this topic we talked
very clearly about the difference between those two. The specific energy of a fuel is the energy
released per unit mass. The energy of a fuel is the energy released per unit volume. So if we look at
the ratio there the joules can cancel out and actually we can do this can't we?
Hmm well that's a unit of volume that's a unit of mass which is effectively volume over mass
which is equal to 1 over density. So the answer is B. Question 14 the Sankey diagram shows the energy
transfers in a nuclear power station. Electrical power output of the power station is a thousand
megawatts. What is the thermal power loss in the heat exchanger? So what's this? Well the
electrical energy output is a thousand megawatts and that is the equivalent of four squares
and look the thermal energy loss in the heat exchanger is four squares as well so that must
also be a thousand megawatts. The thermal loss in the turbine is two squares so that's 500 megawatts
so our answer is a thousand and just to be for completeness our total input is all these added
together which is 2500 megawatts. This is where I leave you and as a reminder I am leaving you
because eventually you have to start working on these past paper problems yourself. I've given you
some really good exam tips here. We've talked about the areas under graph and how to spot what
they mean. We've talked about this concept of work done equals energy transferred and I've talked
you through a number of different types of energy power and efficiency questions. I've left you with
some easy ones after me and then two little difficult ones at the end. They're not physics
difficult, they're maths difficult so just relax and try and do them yourself and I will see you
in step three of the tribe success path which has propelled your progress. Let's go, bye.